Westbrook Free Lectureship Records, 1910-1990 WFIS.93-003
Wagner Free Institute of Science
Westbrook Free Lectureship Records
Bulk, 1912-1924
1910-1990
WFIS.93-003
Wagner Free Institute of Science
1.0 Linear feet 2 containers
Richard Brodhead Westbrook (1820-1899) was a Trustee of the Wagner Free Institute of Science from 1884 until his death in 1899. In his will, he established an endowment for the Richard B. Westbrook Free Lectureship as a means to encourage open discourse on scientific subjects, especially disputed questions in science and the theories of Evolution. This collection contains correspondence, announcements, syllabi, notes and newspaper clippings relating to the Westbrook Free Lectureship from its beginning in 1912 through 1990. The Lecture Records series is the most in depth. Full text is available for the 1918 lecture, and notes and synopses are present for other years.
Wagner Free Institute of Science.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research use.
Preservation/Conservation Notes
Some of the folders contain handwritten notes on very brittle, brown paper; these records were photocopied on acid free paper and placed with the originals.
Those items in folder 8 which were not already in envelopes were wrapped in folded sheets of micro-chamber paper; most of these records have mold.
Records in folder 11 (1913 Lecture) were humidified and flattened.
Papers in folders 17 and 23 have mold and are decomposing. The original lectures were photocopied on acid free paper to create use/preservation copies; the originals are interleaved with micro-chamber paper.
Papers in folders 27.2 and 28.2 are very brittle. The original records were photocopied on acid free paper to create use/preservation copies; the originals are interleaved with micro-chamber paper.
Folder 30 contains newspaper clippings. The original clippings were photocopied on acid free paper to create use/preservation copies; originals are encapsulated in Mylar.
Related Materials in the WFIS Archives
Collection 90-001, Wagner Free Institute of Science Director's Files, Instruction records series: Contains correspondence about the Westbrook Lectureship.
Collection 93-006, the Annual Announcement of the Wagner Free Institute of Science and collection 98-049, the Bulletin of the Wagner Free Institute of Science: contain descriptions of some of the Westbrook lectures.
Biographical Sketch of Richard Brodhead Westbrook
Richard Brodhead Westbrook was born February 8, 1820 in Pike County, Pennsylvania. By 1839 he had obtained a license to preach. At 21 he married Sara Hall; they had four children together. He remained a Methodist Episcopal preacher until 1852, but left the Methodist Church that year.
Beginning in 1853 Westbrook served as a Presbyterian pastor in Burlington, NJ. Around the same time he was awarded an honorary Master of Arts (A.M.) degree from Princeton University. In 1854 he was serving as the secretary of the American Sunday School Union. Westbrook received another honorary degree, Doctor of Divinity (D.D.), in 1860 from Washington College (Maryland). Three years later (1863) he received a degree in law from New York University and admittance to the New York State Bar. The following year he relinquished his responsibilities as a Presbyterian minister.
Sometime before 1871 Westbrook purchased 5,000 acres of land in Cambria County, PA. He stopped practicing law in order to mine that property for coal. In 1871 he married Henrietta Payne; they lived together on the Cambria County lands until 1878. By 1876 Westbrook was chairman of the Sonman Land & Coal Company. He sold his mining land and retired to Philadelphia in 1882. His first wife, Hall, died that same year.
In 1885 Westbrook was serving as president of the American Secular Union. That year he also became treasurer of the Wagner (he had been a WFIS trustee since the previous year). He remained a trustee until his death. In his will, signed 1897, Westbrook bestowed $10,000, upon the death of his wife, to establish a trust that would serve as the foundation for the Westbrook Free Lectureship. He wanted WFIS to use the funds to procure lecturers who would discuss evolution, anthropology, geology, astronomy, natural sciences, and ethical questions as they relate to scientific developments; however, his will explicitly stated that all “… strictly religious questions [were] to be excluded.” Richard Brodhead Westbrook died August 21, 1899; the lectures began in 1912.
As a writer, Westbrook produced a number of works: Marriage and Divorce (1883), Man: Whence and Whither? (1884), The Clerical Combination to Influence Civil Legislation on Marriage and Divorce (1887), Girard’s Will and Girard College Theology (1888), A Few Plain Words Regarding Church Taxation (1890), Shall the Bible Be Read in our Public Schools? (1890), The Bible: Whence and What? (1890), and The Eliminator: or, Skeleton Keys to Sacerdotal Secrets (1894). Henrietta Payne Westbrook, a graduate of Women’s Medical College in 1880, was author of The Actor’s Child: A Study of Heredity or Anti-Natal Influences (1900) and Westbrook Drives (1902).
Sources:
Sonman Land and Coal Company. The Sonman Land and Coal Co. (Limited). Rare, Am 1876 Sonman, Library Company of Philadelphia, Philadelphia, PA.
Wagner Free Institute of Science Biographical Files. Dr. R. B. Westbrook Dead at Pascoag (89-040), August 22, 1899, The Library of the Wagner Free Institute of Science, Philadelphia, PA.
Wagner Free Institute of Science Biographical Files. Excerpt from the will of Richard Brodhead Westbrook, [n.d.], The Library of the Wagner Free Institute of Science, Philadelphia, PA.
Wagner Free Institute of Science Biographical Files. Passed Away-Death of Richard Brodhead Westbrook, D.D., LL.D. (89-040), [n.d.], The Library of the Wagner Free Institute of Science, Philadelphia, PA.
Wagner Free Institute of Science. 1899. In Memoriam: Richard Brodhead Westbrook. Proceedings of the Occasion of a Memorial Meeting, the Hall of the Wagner Free Institute of Science, 25 October.
Scope and Contents note
The collection contains the administrative records of WFIS’ Westbrook Free Lectureship. Most of the collection documents the Institute’s efforts to obtain and schedule speakers for the yearly lecture series. Materials in the record group include lecture announcements, syllabi, expense records, correspondence and handwritten notes.
The earliest material dates from 1910, and records are as recent as 1990; the bulk of the collection deals with the lectures which occurred between 1912 and 1924, and lectures from 1946 to 1973. A gap in records exists between 1924 and 1946; however, some of the syllabi for lectures which fall within that year are in the Instruction series.
The Lecture Records series is the most in depth. Along with administrative records, full text is available for the 1918 lecture, and notes and synopses are present for other years.
Hrdlička, Aleš, 1869-1943; Jastrow, Morris, 1861-1921; Jennings, H.S. (Herbert Spencer), 1868-1947; Mead, Margaret, 1901-1978; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946; Scott, William Berryman, 1858-1947; Simpson, George Gaylord, 1902-1984; Wagner Free Institute of Science.; Westbrook, Richard B., (Richard Brodhead); Wiley, Harvey W. (Harvey Washington), 1844-1930; Announcements; Correspondence; Education; Lectures and lecturing; Richard Westbrook lectures of the Wagner Free Institute of Science; Science--Study and teaching; Syllabi
- Instruction, 1915-1990; Series 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Four folders; Syllabi and Announcements arranged chronologically; materials provide name of lecturer and time, place and topic of lecture.
  - Lecture Syllabi, 1915, 1918, 1921, 1922-1926 (Folder 1)
  - Lecture Syllabi, 1927-1938 (Folder 2)
  - Lecture Syllabi, 1939-1945, 1990 (Folder 3)
  - Poster Announcements for Lectures, 1936-1939, 1944, 1945 (Folder 4)
- Administrative Records, 1951-1963; Series 2
  Two folders; assorted materials arranged chronologically within folders; materials provide scientific ideas of the day and summaries of lecture audiences.
  - Lecture Topics, 1951-1961 (Folder 5)
    Contents
    Magazine clippings, handwritten notes, agenda, course description, publisher circulars
  - Attendance Statistics, 1954, 1963 (Folder 6)
    Annotated bulletin and lists of all-time highs
- Financial Records, 1910-1982; Series 3
  Three folders and three ledger books (housed separately); assorted materials arranged chronologically within folders; materials provide information on expenditures related to lectures.
  - Estate Records, 1910-1935 (Folder 7)
    Correspondence, Schedule of Distribution, list of books donated
  - Bank Records, 1912-1925 (Folder 8)
    Check stubs, check book, account book (Enveloped)
  - Expense Records, 1913-1916, 1936 (Folder 9)
    Cancelled check, vouchers, purchase orders, expense report, bills, receipts
  - Ledger Books, 1934-1982 (Box 2)
    Note:
    These three ledger books were originally part of Accession 99-109, but were moved to 93-003 in July 2010.
- Lecture Records, 1912-1973; Series 4
  Forty-five folders; folders arranged chronologically beginning with the earliest lecture; folder contents arranged chronologically beginning with the most recent record. Most materials are correspondence related to the arrangement of the lecture; however, syllabi and lecture synopses provide brief summaries of the lectures. Full copy is available for the 1918 lectures.
  - 1912 Lecture, 1912-1913 (Folder 10)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, and syllabus
    Ancient Civilization of Babylonia and Assyria, Morris Jastrow, Professor of Semitic Languages, University of Pennsylvania
    Lecture dates: February 13, 20, 27, March 5, 12, 1912
  - 1913 Lecture (Folder 11)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, Price lecture synopsis, and syllabus
    Conservation of Natural Resources, Gifford Pinchot, President, National Conservation Association; Marshall O. Leighton, Cheif Hydrographer, US Geological Survey; Overton W. Price, Vice President and Treasurer, National Conservation Association; and Joseph A. Holmes, Director, Department of the Interior, Bureau of Mines
    Lecture dates: January 13, 25, February 1, 8, 1913
    (Humidified and flattened: July 2007)
  - 1914 Lecture, 1913-1914 (Folder 12)
    Correspondence
    The Theory of Evolution, William Berryman Scott, Blair Professor of Geology and Paleontology, Princeton University
    Lecture dates: February 14, 21, 28, March 7, 14, 21, 1914
  - 1914 Lecture, 1916 (Folder 13)
  - 1916 Lecture, 1916-1920 (Folder 14)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, syllabus
    Aspects of Modern Astronomy, John Anthony Miller, Mathematics and Astronomy Professor, Swarthmore College
    Lecture dates: February 19, 26, March 4, 11, 21, 1914
  - 1917 Lecture, 1917-1923 (Folder 15)
    Correspondence ( re: Jennings publication), promotional materials, syllabus
    Life, Death and Reproduction, Heredity and Evolution in the Simplest Organisms, H.S. Jennings, Henry Walters Professor of Zoology, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD
    Lecture dates: March 6, 13, 20, 27, 1917
  - 1918 Lecture - Preservation Copy of Lecture I (Folder 16)
    Preservation copy of Lecture I - Use Copy
    The Chemistry, Nutritive Value and Economy of Foods: Definition of Food, Characters of Food, Analysis of Foods, Harvey W. Wiley, Director, Bureau of Foods, Sanitation and Health, Good Housekeeping, Washington DC
    Lecture date: March 5, 1918
  - 1918 Lecture - Original Lecture I (Folder 17)
    Original Lecture I - Do Not Use ( Mold; interleaving: July 2007)
  - 1918 Lecture - Preservation Copy of Lecture II (Folder 18)
    Preservation Copy of Lecture II - Use Copy
    The Chemistry, Nutritive Value and Economy of Foods: Quantities of Food, Calories, Metabolism, Harvey W. Wiley, Director, Bureau of Foods, Sanitation and Health, Good Housekeeping, Washington DC
    Lecture date: March 12, 1918
  - 1918 Lecture - Original Lecture II (Folder 19)
    Original Lecture II - Do Not Use ( mold)
  - 1918 Lecture - Preservation Copy of Lecture III (Folder 20)
    Preservation Copy of Lecture III - Use Copy
    The Chemistry, Nutritive Value and Economy of Foods: Food Production, Food Industries, Harvey W. Wiley, Director, Bureau of Foods, Sanitation and Health, Good Housekeeping, Washington DC
    Lecture date: March 19, 1918
  - 1918 Lecture - Original Lecture III (Folder 21)
    Original Lecture III - Do Not Use ( mold)
  - 1918 Lecture - Preservation Copy of Lecture IV (Folder 22)
    Preservation Copy of Lecture IV - Use Copy
    The Chemistry, Nutritive Value and Economy of Foods: Food Conservation, Relation of Food to Health, Food and Efficiency, Food Economy, Harvey W. Wiley, Director, Bureau of Foods, Sanitation and Health, Good Housekeeping, Washington DC
    Lecture date: March 26, 1918
  - 1918 Lecture - Original Lecture IV (Folder 23)
    Original Lecture IV - Do Not Use ( Mold; Interleaving: July 2007)
  - 1919 Lecture, 1919-1920 (Folder 24)
    The Origin and Antiquity of the American Indian, Alex Hrdlicka, Curator, Division of Physical Anthropology, U.S. National Museum, Smithsonian Institute, Washington DC
    Lecture dates: March 8, 15, 22, 29, 1919
  - 1920 Lecture, 1919-1920 (Folder 25)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, lecture synopses
    Chemistry and Civilization, Allerton S. Cushman, Director, Institute of Industrial Research, Inc., Washington DC; Ex-Lieutenant Colonel, Ordnance Department, USA
    Lecture dates: March 13, 20, 27, and April 3, 1920
  - 1924 Lecture, 1923-1924 (Folder 26)
    Correspondence, syllabi
    The Distribution of American Indian Traits, Clark Wissler, Curator-in-Chief, Division of Anthropology, American Museum of Natural History, New York, NY
    Lecture dates: February 2, 9, 16, 23, 1924
  - 1946 Lecture, 1945-1946 (Folder 27)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, preservation photocopies, handwritten notes, lecture figures, memos, lecture synopses
    Electrical Communications - Its Roots and Branches, J. Owen Perrine, Assistant Vice President, American Telephone and Telegraph, Co., New York, NY
    Lecture dates: April 12, 18, 26, 1946
  - 1946 Lecture - Preservation Copy of Lecture Notes (Folder 27.1)
    Preservation copy of lecture notes - Use Copy
  - 1946 Lecture - Original Lecture Notes (Folder 27.2)
    Original Lecture Notes - Do Not Use ( Brittle; Interleaving: July 2007)
  - 1947 Lecture, 1946-1947 (Folder 28)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, preservation photocopies, handwritten notes, lecture synopses
    The Glacial Ages, Richard Foster Flint, Professor, Yale University, Department of Geology, New Haven, CT
    Lecture dates: April 11, 12, 18, 1947
  - 1947 Lecture - Preservation Copy of Lecture Notes (Folder 28.1)
  - 1947 Lecture - Original Lecture Notes, n.d. (Folder 28.2)
    Original lecture notes - Do Not Use ( Brittle; Interleaving: July 2007)
  - 1948 Lecture, 1947-1948 (Folder 29)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, preservation photocopies, hnadwritten notes, lecture synopses
    High Speed Aerodynamics and Jet Propulsions, Courtland D. Perkins, Professor, Princeton University, School of Engineering, Princeton, NJ
    Lecture dates: April 22, 29, 30, 1948
  - 1949 Lecture, 1948-1949 (Folder 30)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, preservation photocopies, handwritten notes, newspaper clippings, press release, lecture synopses ( Encapsulated clippings: July 2007)
    Earth's Resources and Man's Needs, Kirtley F. Mather, Professor, Harvard University, Geological Museum, Department of Geology and Geography, Cambridge, MA
    Lecture dates: April 14, 21, 28, 1949
  - 1950 Lecture, 1949-1950 (Folder 31)
    Evolution and the History of Life, George Gaylord Simpson, Chairman, Department of Geology and Paleontology, American Museum of Natural History, New York, NY
    Lecture Dates: April 6, 13, 20, 1950
  - 1951 Lecture, 1951-1952 (Folder 32)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, preservation photocopies, WFIS Bulletin, lecture synopses
    Exploration of the Atlantic Ocean Basin Maurice Ewing, Columbia University, Department of Geology, LaMont Geological Survey, Palisades, NY
    Lecture dates: April 5, 12, 19, 1951
  - 1952 Lecture, 1951-1952 (Folder 33)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, preservation photocopies, handwritten notes, biographical notes, brief lecture notes
    Radiations: Terrestrial, Atomic, and Cosmic, William F.G. Swann, Director, Bartol Research Foundation of the Franklin Institute, Whittier Place, Swarthmore, PA
    Lecture dates: April 3, 10, 17, 1952
  - 1953 Lecture, 1952-1953; 2002 (Folder 34)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, biographical notes, 2002 example of Mead's signature, lecture synopses
    Cultural Background for Human Invention, Margaret Mead, Associate Curator of Ethnology, The American Museum of Natural History, Department of Anthropology, New York, NY
    Lecture dates: April 16, 30, and May 1, 1953
  - 1954 Lecture, 1953-1954 (Folder 35)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, handwritten notes, biographical notes
    Plant Biology and Man's Progress, Harley H. Bartlett, Professor of Botany, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI
    Lecture dates: April 21, 28, 29, 1954
  - 1955 Lecture, 1954-1955 (Folder 36)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, preservation photocopy, handwritten notes, lecture synopses
    Heredity and the Human Community, Leslie C. Dunn, Director, The Institute for the Study of Human Variation and for Research on the Biological Factors Causing Evolutionary Changes in Populations, Columbia University, Department of Zoology, New York, NY
    Lecture dates: April 14, 21, 28, 1955
  - 1956 Lecture, 1955-1956 (Folder 37)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, handwritten notes, lecture synopses
    Climate and the Modern World, Charles W. Thornthwaite, Director, The Laboratory of Climatology, Elmer, NJ
    Lecture dates: April 12, 19, 26, 1956
  - 1957 Lecture, 1956-1957 (Folder 38)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, handwritten notes, biographical notes, lecture synopses
    Scientific Progress and Human Needs, William Vogt, National Director, Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Inc., New York, NY; George R. Seidel, Technical Advisor, EI du Pont de Nemours and Company, Wilmington, DE; and Maria Telkes, Project Director, New York University, College of Engineering, New York, NY
    Lecture dates: April 4, 11, 18, 1957
  - 1958 Lecture, 1957-1958 (Folder 39)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, preservation photocopy, biographical notes
    The Nature of Human Nature, Hadley Cantril, Senior Counsellor, The Institute for International Social Research, Princeton, NJ
    Lecture dates: April 3, 10, 17, 1958
  - 1959 Lecture, 1958-1959 (Folder 40)
    Correspondence, promotional materials
    Evolution: From the Cosmos to Man, Harlow Shapley, Director, Harvard College Observatory, Harvard University, Department of Astronomy, Cambridge, MA; Conway Zirkle, Professor of Botany, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA; and William L. Straus, Jr., Professor of Anatomy and Physical Anthropology, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Department of Anatomy, Baltimore, MD
    Lecture dates: April 2, 9, 16, 1959
  - 1960 Lecture, 1959-1960 (Folder 41)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, preservation photocopies, handwritten notes
    Early Man, Carleton S. Coon, Professor of Anthropology, The University Museum, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA; and William W. Howells, Professor of Anthropology, Harvard University, Department of Anthropology, Peabody Museum, Cambridge, MA
    Lecture dates: April 21, 28, 1960
  - 1961 Lecture, 1960-1961 (Folder 42)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, handwritten notes
    Prospects of the Space Age, Kurt R. Stehling, Scientist, Office of Program Planning and Evaluation, National Aeronautics and Space Administration, Washington DC
    Lecture dates: March 30, and April 6, 13, 1961
  - 1962 Lecture, 1961-1962 (Folder 43)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, handwritten notes, brief lecture notes
    Problems of the Earth's Crust, Walter H. Bucher, Emeritus Professor of Geology, Columbia University, New York, NY; Consultant, Humble Oil & Refining Company, Houston, TX
  - 1963 Lecture, 1962-1963 (Folder 44)
    Correspondence ( re: theft at WFIS), promotional materials, preservation photocopies, handwritten notes, biographical notes
    The Study of Human Behavior in Disaster, George W. Baker, Associate Program Director for Life and Social Sciences Facilities, Office of Institutional Programs, National Science Foundation, Washington, DC and Technical Director, Disaser Researach Group, Division of Anthropology and Psychology, National Academy of Sciences, National Research Council, Washington, DC; Ira A. Cisin, Director, Social Studies Project, George Washington University, Washington, DC; John P. Gillin, Research Professor, University of Pittsburgh, Department of Anthropology, Pittsbugh, PA and U.S. Naval Ordnance Test Station, Department of the Navy, China Lake, CA
    Lecture dates: April 11, 18, 25, 1963
  - 1966 Lecture (Folder 45)
    Correspondence, handwritten notes, Oliver Wendell Holmes Association (OWHA) statment of purpose, director's report, promotional materials, sign-in sheet, attendance list
  - 1966 Lecture, 1966-1967 (Folder 46)
    The Impact of Science and Technology on Modern Life, Kirtley F. Mather, President, OWHA, New York, NY; retired professor, Harvard University, Geological Museum, Department of Geology and Geography, Cambridge, MA
    Lecture Dates: October 18, 19, 20, 1966 (at Empire Room, Wanamaker's, Philadelphia, PA)
  - 1966 Lecture (Folder 47)
    Correspondence, contact information, handwritten notes
  - 1967 Lecture, 1967-1968 (Folder 48)
    Correspondence, promotional materials, director's report, handwritten notes, lecture synopses
    Galaxies and Mankind, Harlow Shapley, former director, Harvard College Observatory, Harvard University, Department of Astronomy, Cambridge, MA; President, American Association for the Advancement of Science
    Lecture dates: October 17, 18, 19, 1967 (at Empire Room, Wanamaker's, Philadelphia, PA)
  - 1967 Lecture (Folder 49)
    Correspondence, purpose of OWHA, OWHA questionnaires, handwritten notes, attendance list
  - 1972 Lecture (Folder 50)
    Identification of Sedimentary Environments in Reservoir Sandstones, Robert Berg, Lecturer, American Association of Petroleum Geologists, Tulsa, OK; Professor, Texas A&M University, Department of Geology, College Station, TX
    Lecture dates: March 6, 1972 (at Bryn Mawr College Science Center, Bryn Mawr, PA)
  - 1973 Lecture (Folder 51)
    What and Where are those UFOs? Donald M. Menzel, Paine Professor of Practical Astronomy, Harvard College, Cambridge, MA; Research Scientist, Astrophysical Observatory, Smithsonian Institute, Cambridge, MA
    Lecture dates: November 8, 1973 (at the Free Library of Philadelphia, Northeast Regional Library, Philadelphia, PA)